Preliminary Inventory to the National Writers Union Records WAG.026
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Writers Union Records
1976-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Writers Union (U.S.). New York Local
WAG.026
46.25 Linear Feet (48 boxes)
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Writers Union (NWU) represents freelance writers throughout the United States. It was formed in 1981 during the Writers' Congress held in New York City. By the end of the year, the organization had more than 1000 dues-paying members and was actively organizing around the country. The Union convened annual delegates' assemblies, offered a low-cost health and dental insurance plan for freelancers, instituted a committee structure, and produced materials to assist their membership such as a model book contract, a survey of New England publications and a checklist of questions for writers to use when bidding on jobs. Most significantly, the Union began to win contracts with periodicals, such as Mother Jones, Columbia Journalism Review, In These Times, and Los Angeles Weekly. In 1981, the NWU affiliated with the United Auto Workers (UAW) as Local 1981. The NWU's fight for author retention of copyright in electronically published articles culminated in its victory in Tasini v. New York Times Co. in 2001. As of 2011, the NWU has over 1,500 members in fifteen locals.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists mostly of the records of the NWU's national office, although some material came from the New York and Los Angeles Locals. The records include National Executive Board minutes, officers' files, internal e-mails, local and national newsletters, membership applications and grievances. Also included are materials from Delegate Assembly meetings, which include minutes, reports, agendas and notes. Finally, there is particularily extensive documentation of the landmark lawsuit Tasini v. New York Times Co.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the National Writers Union, NY Local in 1985. The accession number associated with this gift is 1985.021. Additional materials were donated in 2009 and 2012. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 2009.070 and 2012.007.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Authors and publishers.; Authors |x Labor unions |z United States.; Copyright infringement.; Copyright |x Databases.; Copyright |z United States.; Organizing Committee for a National Writers Union (U.S.); Tasini, Jonathan; National Writers Union (U.S.); National Writers Union (U.S.). New York Local; Dubro, Alec; Google Library Project; Reiser, Bob; Sunshine, Alice; New York Times Company; National Writers Union (U.S.). New York Local
- Inventory
  - Alec Dubro (President) Files: Correspondence, Periodicals, and Subject Files, late 1980s-early 1990s (Box 1)
  - Delegates Assembly (includes minutes and information on the decision to affiliate with the United Auto Workers), 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - Alec Dubro (President) Files: Subject Files, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - New York Local Files: Committee Records, Periodicals, and Subject Files (1980-1992); Business, Instructional, Technical, and Electronic (BITE) Division, Diversity Committee (1997-2003), 1980-2003 (Box 4)
  - National Executive Board (including minutes), Conference on Censorship and Culture (1984), Background Material on Publishing and Bookselling: Chain Bookstore Study, 1984-1990 (Box 5)
  - Grievances, 1985-1991 (Box 6)
  - Organizing Campaigns and Correspondence with National Executive Board, 1982-1987 (Box 7)
  - Local Files (especially New York), 1981-1989 (Box 8)
  - Legal and Public Relations Files, 1982-1991 (Box 9)
  - Local Files, Correspondence, Blue Books, Contracts/Agreements (includes Columbia Journalism Review, In These Times, and LA Weekly), 1984-1990 (Box 10)
  - Negotiations, Organizing Campaigns, and Contracts (mostly with Mother Jones and Ms. Magazine), 1983-1992 (Box 11)
  - Negotiations, Organizing Campaigns, and Contracts (including with the Nation), 1985-1990 (Box 12)
  - Negotiations, Organizing Campaigns, Contracts, Blue Books, and Membership Files, 1981-1991 (Box 13)
  - Subject files relating to the formation and early history of the Organizing Committee for a National Writers Union, also includes later files on conferences and other events, 1980-1987 (Box 14)
  - National Executive Board and Delegates Assembly: Meeting Materials and Correspondence, 1983-1987 (Box 15)
  - Alec Dubro (President) Files: Correspondence, Memos, Reports, and Meeting Records (includes folder of correspondence on the refusal of the NWU to publish a classified ad promoting a Holocaust denial group run by an NWU member), 1987-1990 (Box 16)
  - National Executive Board, 1986-1989 (Box 17)
  - Delegates Assembly, 1983-1988 (Box 18)
  - National Executive Board Minutes (1990-1993), Delegates Assembly and Election Records, 1982-1993 (Box 19)
  - Membership and Health Insurance Files, Memos from Alice Sunshine to NWU Locals, and Organizing Files, 1995-2003 (Box 20)
  - Membership and Health Insurance Files, Election Ballots, mid-late 1990s (Box 21)
  - Member Responses to Surveys on Political Views (1999) and Print on Demand Publishing (2000), 1999-2000 (Box 22)
  - Tasini v. New York Times Co., early 1990s-early 2000s (Box 23)
  - Copyright and Fair Use Issues (Legal Files and Publishing Rights Clearinghouse Correspondence) and 2001 Elections, mid 1990s-mid 2000s (Box 24)
  - Jonathan Tasini (President) Files: Various Organizations that Relate to Writers Union, both Nationally and Internationally, 1990s-2000s (Box 25)
  - Legal and Administrative Files (includes material on Google Books controversy), early 1990s-late 2000s (Box 26)
  - Subject Files on Publishers, Legislative Files, and NWU Campaigns, 1990s-2000s (Box 27)
  - Local Files, National Executive Board Meetings (mid 1990s), Delegates Assembly (1997), UAW Affiliation, and Jonathan Tasini (President) E-mails (Box 28)
  - Jonathan Tasini (President) Files: Conferences and Meetings Attended (includes eight 5 1/4'' floppy disks) and Internal E-mails, late 1990s-early 2000s (Box 29)
  - Detailed Handwritten Notes on Activities and Meetings of Unknown Member of National Executive Board, 1990s (Box 30)
  - Contracts, Financial Records, Survey on Book Agents, Legal Files, and General Administrative Files, 1990s-2000s (Box 31)
  - Local and Sublocal Files, 1990s-early 2000s (Box 32)
  - Media Perils Insurance (most of box), Local Files, and 2003 elections, late 1990s-early 2000s (Box 33)
  - Bob Reiser Files on the Organizing Committee for a National Writers Union; Bylaws, Resignations, National Executive Committee Meetings, and Delegates Assemblies, early 1980s-mid 2000s (Box 34)
  - Bob Reiser Files on the Early NWU (includes campaigns, organizing drives, and grievances), 1980s (Box 35)
  - Bob Files on the Early NWU (including strategy documents); Media Perils Insurance and Bay Area Local Files, early 1980s-early 2000s (Box 36)
  - Subject Files, E-mails from Jonathan Tasini (President), late 1980s-mid 2000s (Box 37)
  - Legal Files (mostly covering either Tasini v. New York Times Co. or a dispute with the Boston Globe), late 1990s-early 2000s (Box 38)
  - Early Records of the Organizing Committee for a National Writers Union (including minutes, correspondence, campaign files, and membership applications), 1979-1986 (Box 39)
  - Tasini v. New York Times Co., mid 1990s-early 2000s (Box 40)
  - Local Files, Early Organizing Files, and National Executive Board Meeting (Jan 1998), early 1980s-early 2000s (Box 41)
  - New York Local Files: Conferences, 1987 Blue Book, Steering Committee, and National Executive Board, 1984-1987 (Box 42)
  - Delegates Assembly Agendas, Board and Campaign Reports, Resolutions, Proposals, Stipend Requests, and Constitutions/By-Laws; Information on The Village Voice Campaign and National Book Organizing Committee; Resources on Bargaining and Contracts; "National Writers Union Guide to Book Contracts" by Philip Mattera and Maria Pallante; and Booklet "Authors in the New Information Age: A Working Paper on Electronic Publishing Issues", 1986-1987, 1991, 1993-1998, 2001, 2004 (Box 43)
  - Electronic Databases and Author Copyright Issues; Book Campaign Materials; 1996 Labor Party Convention; Chapters from Manuscript by Jonathan Tasini; 1992 Writers' Rights Day; Steering Committee; and Grievance Committee Materials, 1984-1995 (Box 44)
  - Local Files; National Executive Board Reports, Correspondence, and Minutes; Delegates Assembly; Affiliation Agreements (Ploughshares, International Union, Communications Workers of America, etc.); New York Labor for Peace Materials; and Telecommunications Coalition, mid 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 45)
  - Local Files; National Executive Board Reports, Correspondence, and Minutes; Delegates Assembly; Journalists Committee; Writers' Rights Day; L.A. Weekly Negotiations; and Organizing Files, 1984-1993 (Box 46)
  - National Executive Board Meetings; Organizing Files; The Village Voice and United Auto Workers Agreement; and Penguin USA and Association of American Publishers Negotiations, 1984-1990 (Box 47)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 48)
- Archived Website, Dec 08, 2012-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The National Writers Union (NWU) represents freelance writers throughout the United States. It was formed in 1981 during the Writers' Congress held in New York City. In 1981, the NWU affiliated with the United Auto Workers (UAW) as Local 1981. As of 2011, the NWU has over 1,500 members in fifteen locals. The website contains news and chapter information.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.